{
  "sourceFile": "2020-2021-International-Geography-Bee-Round-2-A-Set.txt",
  "count": 10,
  "items": [
    {
      "qno": 1,
      "question": "This desert's Makgadikgadi [[mahk-gahd-eek-GAH-dee]] salt pan was a lake until approximately 10,000 years ago, and this desert still hosts large subterranean water reserves like Dragon's Breath Cave. Indigenous populations living east of this desert's Okavango inland delta speak Jul'hoan [[jool-HO-ahn]], a dialect of Khoisan. For the point, name this large desert in southern Africa covering much of Botswana and Namibia.",
      "answer": "Kalahari Desert"
    },
    {
      "qno": 2,
      "question": "After passing through the vale Polabí, this river receives the river Orlice [[or-LEE- tseh]] near the city of Hradec Králové [[HRAH-dets krah-LOH-veh]]. This river rises in the Krkonoše [[kreh-koh-NOH-sheh]] Mountains of Bohemia, near the Czech-Polish border. The cities of Berlin and Prague reside within this river's sizeable drainage basin, which covers most of the former state of East Germany. For the point, name this central European river which empties into the North Sea after passing through Hamburg.",
      "answer": "Elbe [[EL-buh]] River"
    },
    {
      "qno": 3,
      "question": "This island includes Nanwan Monkey Island, which is actually a peninsula. This island's major waterways include the Xinwu [[SHIN-WOO]] and Nandu Rivers. This island's largest body of water is the artificial reservoir of Songtao. This island is governed from the city of Haikou [[HAI-KOH]], which sits on the nearby island of Haidian [[HAI-DYAHN]]. For the point, name this island, which makes up a province of the southern coast of mainland China.",
      "answer": "Hainan"
    },
    {
      "qno": 4,
      "question": "The Kalambo River ends in a 772-foot single-drop waterfall feeding into this lake. This lake's primary outflow is the Lukuga River, which traverses the northern edge of the Katanga Plateau. Lake Kivu drains into this lake via the Ruzizi, this lake's primary inflow. This lake is shared by four countries, including Burundi and Zambia. For the point, name this second- largest lake in the world by volume, the largest rift lake in Africa.",
      "answer": "Lake Tanganyika"
    },
    {
      "qno": 5,
      "question": "This archipelago's largest island is separated from the islands of Picton, Lennox, and Nueva by the Beagle Channel, named for the ship Charles Darwin used to traverse the region. This archipelago is bounded to the south by the Drake Passage, beyond which is Antarctica, and to the north by the Straits of Magellan, which separates this archipelago from the rest of Patagonia. For the point, name this archipelago shared by Argentina and Chile at the southern tip of South America.",
      "answer": "Tierra del Fuego 2020-21 V/JV Spring Geography Bee V/JV Spring Geography Bee – Round 2"
    },
    {
      "qno": 6,
      "question": "This island is home to statues of little men with mushrooms on their heads known as harubangs. This island's highest point is Hallasan, which is home to the Jonjaamji Pagoda. Nearly 300 people perished en route to this island in an April 2014 ferry disaster. This island's primary port is the city of Seogwipo [[SUH-GWEE-POH]]. For the point, name this island off the southern coast of South Korea, a popular honeymoon destination.",
      "answer": "Jeju Island"
    },
    {
      "qno": 7,
      "question": "In 1968, National Park Service director George Hartzog put an end to this national park's annual Firefall event at Glacier Point. This national park's O'Shaughnessy Dam supplies water and electricity to over two million people in San Francisco and the Bay Area. Ansel Adams photographed this national park's rock formations, including El Capitan and Half Dome. For the point, name this national park located in California's Sierra Nevada mountains.",
      "answer": "Yosemite National Park"
    },
    {
      "qno": 8,
      "question": "As this river passes by the town of Sioma, it forms the Ngonye Falls. Features of this river include the Kariba and Cahora Bassa dams. This river passes over the Devil's Cataracts on its way to the Indian Ocean and includes Africa's largest waterfall, the Victoria Falls. For the point, name this southern African river that forms the border between Zambia and Zimbabwe.",
      "answer": "Zambezi River"
    },
    {
      "qno": 9,
      "question": "Along with Haryana, a state named for this region is served by the capital city Chandigarh [[chahn-DEE-gahr]], while Lahore [[luh-HORE]] is the capital and main city of another state named for this region. This region's namesake language is the only tonal Indo- European language and was used to write the Adi Granth. For the point, name this region divided by India and Pakistan, the homeland of Sikhism.",
      "answer": "Punjab"
    },
    {
      "qno": 10,
      "question": "This region is home to the Bingtuan paramilitary group, which was originally founded to protect against Soviet aggression. This region was home to the Dzungars before a Qing [[CHING]] genocide occurred. This region is located north of Tibet and contains the Tarim Basin. Administered from the city of Ürümqi, for the point, what is this autonomous region of western China, the ethnic homeland of the Uyghur [[WEE-guhr]] people?",
      "answer": "Xinjiang [[SHIN-JYAHNG]] Uyghur Autonomous Region"
    }
  ]
}